Sofia Alere

Full-Stack Software Engineer

Ochicago, IL 🛮 sofalere@gmail.com 🔘 sofalere 🥆 sofalere.com

PROFILE

Professional Software Engineer located in Chicago with expertise in Node.js and Ruby ecosystems. I bring a strong commitment to organization and effective communication to each project in which I am involved. My most recent accomplishment includes the development of Sundial, a sophisticated cron job monitoring and management system.

SKILLS

Tools & Databases Git/Github, PostgreSQL, MongoDB, SQLite, Docker, Postman, NGINX, Linux, Bash, HTTP, BCrypt, RSpec, Jest

Cloud Digital Ocean, AWS (EC2, IAM), Heroku, Fly.io, VPCs, Render

Languages & Runtimes Javascript (ES6+), Ruby, Golang, SQL, HTML/CSS, Node.js

Libraries, Frameworks, Misc Express, Sinatra, React/Redux, JQuery, Handlebars, SOAP, REST, XML, WebSockets, SSE

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

2023 present

Software Engineer & Co-Creator, Sundial

Sundial is an open-source cron job monitoring and management system that provides job execution data and alerts, centralized error logs, and the ability to perform CRUD operations on jobs in crontabs across multiple nodes.

- Developed a suite of command-line scripts that provides users a simple integration of Sundial to their existing cron jobs. (Node.js, Javascript)
- Transformed central service set up from a 10-step+ to a 2-step process by containerizing server code. (DockerHub images, Docker Compose)
- Eliminated all installation dependencies on target nodes by packaging scripts into executable binaries using the 'pkg'
- Implemented a RESTful API facilitating app component communication and persistence of cron job execution information. (Node.js, Express, PostgreSQL)
- Decoupled complex logic required to react to non-events from database entities utilizing Task Queues. (PostgreSQL 'pgboss')
- Constructed a responsive dashboard that provides real-time data. (React, Material UI, SSE's)
- Ensured availability by using systemd's unit files to daemonize the HTTP Express server responsible for allowing communication from the service to a node's crontab.
- Designed load tests to determine Sundial's performance under several conditions, observing a 0% failure rate up to 200 concurrent monitored jobs. (Grafana k6)
- Increased security on network connected multi-node set ups through requiring JWT Tokens and API Keys.
- Provided an alternate, more secure set up with instructions on how to deploy Sundial on Digital Ocean VPCs.
- Authored Sundial's comprehensive technical case study ...
- Collaborated remotely with a team of four engineers across three time zones, utilizing Agile workflow practices such as daily stand-ups and pair programming. (Github, Slack, Trello)

2021 - 2023

Software Engineer, Self Employed

Developed freelance and open-source projects.

Shopify Southern Marsh Promotion:

- Identified and debugged errors in promotional logic in a **Shopify** backend.
- Enhanced resilience of codebase segment through re-factoring it in an Object-Oriented Programming (OOP) paradigm. (Ruby)

Inquiry Hub:

- Developed an application that aids in debugging web-hooks by receiving and displaying them in real-time. (React, Express, NGINX, DO, PM2)
- Enhanced scalability by separating relational data and variable request body data to an RDBSM and a noSQL DB. (PostgreSQL, MongoDB)

2017 – 2021 Owner & Professional Yachting Contractor, Sea Nemo

Orchestrated excellent service on luxury yachts as a part of multiple skilled teams.

- Fostered a collaborative and positive work environment through developing strong connections with other team-members and guests.
- Revamped training protocols and personally mentored several new staff with a focus on continuous professional development.

EDUCATION

2021 - 2023 Launch School

Foundations focused software engineering program where I studied the fundamentals of backend and frontend programming, database design, networking, and data driven systems design.